A Guide to the Papers of Alice Rice Jaffe, 1807-1950
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Alice Rice Jaffe 1807-1950
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
17-2B1
2 Hollinger document cases, .83 linear feet
Jaffe, Alice Rice
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
A gift from Alice R. Jaffe, June 1977.
Biographical Information
Alice Rice Jaffe was an art teacher at Old Dominion College / Old Dominion University in the 1960's and 1970's. Jaffe received her A.B. from Vassar College. She was married to the late Louis I. Jaffe, editor of the Virginian Pilot from 1919 to 1950.
Scope and Content
The material in this collection relates to people in Alice Jaffe's life, rather than to Alice Jaffe personally. These persons include: Louis I. Jaffe, her husband and editor of the Virginian Pilot from 1919 to 1950; Colonel Henry Rice, her father; and Captain Samuel Davis, an ancestor and ship's captain. A part of the collection includes materials on the first two decades of growth of the Norfolk Division of William and Mary which later became Old Dominion College and then Old Dominion University. These may have been collected by Louis Jaffe in his role as editor or through other Norfolk civic involvements. Materials related to her ancestor, Captain Samuel Davis whose papers date from 1807 to 1817. The remainder of the collection dates from 1919 to 1950.
Index Terms
Jaffe, Alice Rice--Family; Jaffe, Alice Rice--Friends and associates; College teachers--Virginia--Norfolk; Old Dominion University--Faculty; Old Dominion College--Faculty; Norfolk College of William and Mary--Faculty; Pamphlets; Letters (correspondence); Legal documents; Brochures; Estimates; Photographs; Legal documents; Sheet music
Contents List
- Norfolk Division of William and Mary 1938-1948
  This series includes correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, and brochures regarding the early formation and growth of the Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary from 1938 to 1948. Many of the documents are addressed to or copied to Mr. Louis Jaffe, Alice Jaffe's husband and editor of the Virginian Pilot at the time. Materials are arranged chronologically.
  Chronological
  - Pamphlet: Some Facts about The Norfolk Division, College of William and Mary, and its Services to Parent College and Community (1938) 1938 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Miscellaneous news articles on William and Mary 1939 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Letter from Public Welfare Director H. G. Parker to Louis Jaffe, William D. Fawcett, and Col. James Mann April 29, 1941 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Letter from City Manager Charles B. Borland to Norfolk Council President Joseph D. Wood, with attached copy of committee report 1941 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Report of Charles J. Duke, Jr. to President John Stewart Bryan of the College of William and Mary September 5, 1941 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Booklet: Programs for Training the High School Graduate in Skills Valuable in Time of War, Norfolk Division January 1942 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Letter from Charles J. Duke, Jr. to Louis I. Jaffe, February 18, 1942, with accompanying report of Mr. Duke to President John Stewart Bryan of the College of William and Mary February 5, 1942 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - News release of October 1, 1944, on the establishment of a vocational school at the Norfolk Division October 1, 1944 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - News release of May 27, 1946, on appointment of Lewis Webb as Director of the Norfolk Division May 27, 1946 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Memorandum on the Progress of the Norfolk Division since June 1941, Presented to the Board of Visitors June 4, 1946 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Letter from Charles Duke to Governor William Tuck regarding the consolidation of the educational facilities of the St. Helena Extension and the Norfolk Division March 22, 1948 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Report of committee to study Extensions, to the Rector and The Board of Visitors, College of William and Mary n.d. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Bulletin of Present Facilities and Plans for Future Development, Norfolk Division of the College of William and Mary and Virginia Polytechnic Institute (Box-folder 1:13)
- Col. Henry Rice
  This series relates to the building of a house for year round occupancy at Virginia Beach in 1936 by Alice Jaffe's father, Col. Henry Rice. Included are price estimates, brochures, bills, construction plans, and other related materials. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Alphabetical
  - Construction Papers- Brochures (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Construction Papers- Materials (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Construction Papers- Methods of Construction and Plans (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Construction Papers- Price Estimates & Bills (Box-folder 1:17)
- Captain Samuel Davis
  This series relates to Captain Samuel Davis, a ship's captain, citizen of Norfolk, Virginia, and an ancestor of Alice Jaffe. The series is broken into two sub-series: A. Correspondence and B. Legal Documents.
  - Correspondence - Captain Samuel Davis 1810-1817
    This sub-series contains correspondence regarding U.S. trade with Britain and France. Material is arranged chronologically and dates from 1810 to 1817.
    - Correspondence - Captain Samuel Davis 1810 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Correspondence - Captain Samuel Davis 1815 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Correspondence - Captain Samuel Davis 1817 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Legal documents 1807-1810
    This sub-series contains legal documents including a ship's roster for the American Barque Petersburg, a letter from the Collector of Norfolk requesting safe overseas passage for Captain Davis, and a document regarding the sale of a slave to Samuel Davis. Material is arranged chronologically, and dates from 1807 to 1810.
    - Sale of Slave to Samuel Davis September 22, 1807 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Letter from the Collector of Norfolk requesting safe overseas passage for Captain Samuel Davis January 14, 1809 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Ship's Roster for the American Barque Petersburg March 8, 1810 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Louis I. Jaffe 1919-1950
  This series contains a booklet with a compilation of articles and speeches by Alice Jaffe's husband, Louis Jaffe who was the editor for the Virginian Pilot from 1919 until his death in 1950. He won the Pulitzer Price for Editorial Writing in 1929 for An Unspeakable Act of Savagery, which condemned lynching. This compilation includes this editorial, and his other famous editorial The Baby Magnolia (1920). Other topics include: the press, the Virginian Pilot, Norfolk, anti-lynching laws and race relations, and introductions of speakers such as Robert Frost, World War II.
  - Articles and Speeches by Louis I. Jaffe, Editor, Norfolk Virginian-Pilot 1919-1950 (Box-folder 2:7)
- Miscellaneous 1938
  This series contains a birthday card with an illustrated map of Virginia, a portrait of the presentation of the Norfolk Mace to the Corporation of Norfolk by Robert Dinwiddie, Governor of Virginia in 1754, and sheet music from the records of the ODU School of Arts and Letters. Material is arranged alphabetically.
  Alphabetically
  - Birthday card with illustration of the map of Virginia (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Photo of Norfolk Mace 1938 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Sheet Music Covers (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Sheet Music (Box-folder 2:11)